Finding Aid for the Mctyeire-Baskervill Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
- Papers of Janie McTyeire Baskervill
  - Family and V.U.-related Manuscripts (Box 2, Folder 14-20)
    - "Inspiration of Difficulty" (2 ms. pages) (Box 2, Folder 14-20)
    - "Kate Marian McTyeire" (7 ms. pages) (Box 2, Folder 14-20)
    - "Founding and early history of Vanderbilt Women's Club" (draft of letter, 5 ms. pages) (Box 2, Folder 14-20)
  - Literary manuscripts - papers read by Janie McTyeire Baskervill before Vanderbilt Women's Club: "The Women of Shakespeare" (41 ms. pages), "Hamlet" (42 ms. pages), "Scottish Poetry" (48 ms. pages) (Box 2, Folder 21-33)
- Papers of William Mellone Baskervill
  - "Southern Literature" address (52 ms. pages) (Box 2, Folder 34-48)
  - "Maurice Thompson" (address)(49 ms. pages) (Box 2, Folder 34-48)
  - Select Poems of Sidney Lanier" (book review) (7 ms. pages) (Box 2, Folder 34-48)
  - "American Literature" (bibliography and notes) (11 pages, ms., in notebook) (Box 2, Folder 34-48)
  - "The Victorian Age" (39 ms. pages in notebook) (Box 2, Folder 34-48)
  - "The Romantic Poets" (9 ms. pages) (Box 2, Folder 34-48)
  - "James Russell Lowell" (2 ms. pages) (Box 2, Folder 34-48)
  - Fragment on Georgian English literature (15 ms. pages) (Box 2, Folder 34-48)
  - Diplomas and certificates from Randolph Macon College (5 items) and universities of Leipzig and Heidelberg (7 items) (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Other German items (4 items) (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Wofford College resolutions (2 items) (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Article on William Malone Baskervill (2-page typed carbon) (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Manuscripts by unknown authors: "Charles Samuel Griffith" (11 pages) and notes on Frank A. Vanderbilt (1 page) (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Photographs (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Richard Malcolm Johnston (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Samuel Mintum Peck (3) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Thomas Nelson Page (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified (Amelia McTyeire? Martha Crawford?) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Postcard of Sidney Lanier's birthplace (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 5 small snapshots of Collingsworth Institution (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Holland N. McTyeire's memorandum book, 1866 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Clippings and other printed items (Box 3)
  - Articles by Holland N. McTyeire: "Burying a Father," "My Old Servant, 'Uncle Cy'" (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Articles about Holland N. McTyeire: "Bishop H.N. McTyeire. The Funeral Services," "Undertones of Bishop McTyeire," "MyTyeire Memorial Service," "The Vanderbilt Celebration," "Memorial Address - The Founders and Organizers of Vanderbilt University," "Bishop Holland N. McTyeire" (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Articles mentioning Holland N. McTyeire (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
  - Southern Christian Advocate, Aug. 21, Sept. 4, Oct. 2, Oct 16, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
  - Articles by Janie McTyeire Baskervill: "Bishop Holland N. McTyeire," "Wailter Montgomery McTyeire," "Margaret J. Preston," "Edward Emerson Barnard," "The Twelve World Pictures," parts 1 and 2 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Articles by William Malone Baskervill: "The Anglo-Saxon Version of the 'Epistola Alexandri ad Aristoielem" (dissertation, Leipzig), "Atticus Greene Haygood," "Jaimes Russell Lowell," "Welcome Address" (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
  - Articles about William Malone Baskervill: "William Malone Baskervill" (obituary), "William Malone Baskervill and His Pupils," "The Personal Side of Dr. Baskervill," "Doctor William Malone Baskervill," "Many Writers Acknowledge Literary Debt to Baskervill" (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - W.M. Baskervill's "Southern Writer" series - notices and reviews (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - McTyeire family -- obituaries: Amelia Townsend McTyeire, Kate Marianye McTyeire, Amelia McTyeire Tigert, Mary McTyeire Hamilton, Walter M. McTyeire (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Townsend and Baskervill families -- obituaries and articles: Jane Townsend, Dr. John T. Baskervill, Charles Read Baskervill (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Vanderbilt family: "In Memoria, -- Cornelius Vanderbilt," etc. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Edward Emerson Barnard -- articles not by J.M. Baskervill (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Southern writers - articles not by W.M. Baskervill: articles on James Lane Allen, George W. Cable, Joel Chandler Harris, Thomas Nelson Page, Irwin Russell, Sidney Lanier, Maurice Thompson (Box 3, Folder 20-23)
  - Candler-Kelley controversy (1887) (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
  - Vanderbilt University (Box 3, Folder 26-30)
  - Nashville (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
  - World War I -- maps, etc. (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - A series of lists made in October 1943 by Elizabeth Baskervill Wall, daughter of William Malone and Janie McTyeire Baskervill. (Box 4)
    The lists are of manuscripts, letters and clippings saved by her mother, and include all the items in the present McTyeire- Baskervill. The lists accompanied the material which she sent to Vanderbilt University in 1943, but some items are listed which she did not send, sind other items have apparently been separated from the collection or misplaced since the collection has been in the Joint University Libraries.
    The lists are usefill, since the material is arranged by subject and the compiler comments on the significance of vsirious items, and quotes extensively from others as an aid to identification.
    The lists are as follows:
    Papers relating to Bishop McTyeire, Commodore Vanderbilt etc. (16 pages, typed)
    Papers relating to William Malone Baskervill (15 pages, typed)
    Telegrams to Bishop Holland N. McTyeire (3 pages, typed)
    Clippings and letters pertaining to early history of Vanderbilt University and Barnardiana (5 pages, typed).
  - Envelopes removed from correspondence in box 1 (Box 4)
    Envelopes which are in themselves informative, i.e., with name of writer if not given on letter or with manuscript notes concerning letter, have been kept with the letters.
    Elizabeth Baskervill Wall's pencilled labels for envelopes in which she sent material. Since material has been rearranged, her categories are no longer pertinent, but her labels may be of interest.